[Music]
Wonder by RJ palasio part five Justin Sometimes I think my head is so
big because it is so full of Dreams John Merrick and Bernard Pan's the Elephant
Man Olivia's brother THE FIRST TIME i met Olivia’s little brother, i have to
admit i’m totally taken by surprise.
i shouldn’t be, of course Olivia has told me about his “syndrome.” has even described
what he looks like. but she’s also talked about all his surgeries over the years,
so i guess i assumed he’d be more normal
looking by now. like when a kid is born with a cleft pallet and has plastic
surgery to fix it sometimes you can’t even tell except for the little scar
above the lip. i guess i thought her brother would have some scars here and
there. but not this. i definitely was n expecting to see this little kid in a
baseball cap who’s sitting in front of me right now. actually there are two kids
sitting in front me: one is a total normal looking kid with curly blonde
hair named jack; the other is auggie. i like to think i’m able to hide my
surprise. i hope i do. surprise is one of those emotions that can be hard to fake,
though, whether you’re trying to look surprised when you’re not or trying to
not look surprised when you are. i shake his hand. i shake the other kid’s hand.
don’t want to focus on his face. cool room, I say. are you via’s boyfriend? he
says. i think he’s smiling. olivia pushes down his baseball cap. is that a machine
gun? the blonde kid asked like i haven’t heard that one before. and we talk about
zido for a bit. and then Vias taking my hand and leading me out of the room. as
soon as we close the door behind us, we heard them laughing
laughing. i’m from brooklyn! one of them sings. olivia rolls her eyes as she
smiles. let’s go hang out in my room, she
says. we’ve been dating for 2 months now.
i knew from the moment i saw her, the minute she sat down at our table in the
cafeteria, that i liked her. i couldn’t keep my eyes off of her. really beautiful.
with olive skin and the bluest eyes i’ve ever seen in my life. at first she acted
like she only wanted to be friends. i think she kind of gives off that vibe
without even meaning to. stay back. don’t even bother. she doesn’t flirt like some
other girls do. she looks you right in the eye when she talks to you, like she’s
daring you. so i just kept looking her right in the eye, too, like i was staring
her right back. and then i asked her out and she said yes, which rocked. she’s an
awesome girl and i love hanging out with her. she didn’t tell me about august
until our third date.
i think she used the phrase “a crano facial abnormality” to describe his face.
or maybe it was crano facial anomaly.” i know the one word she didn’t use was
“deformed,” though, because that word would have registered with me. so, what did you
think? she asked me nervously the second were inside her room. are you shocked? no,
i lie. she smiles and looks away. you’re
shocked. i’m not, i assure her. he’s just
like what you said he’d be. she nods and
plops down on her bed. kind of cute how she still has a lot of stuffed animals
on her bed. she takes one of them, a polar bear, without thinking and puts it in her
lap. i sat down on the rolling chair by her desk. her room is immaculate. when i
was little, she says, there were lots of kids who never came back for a second play
date i mean, lots of kids.
i even had friends who wouldn’t come to my birthdays because he would be there.
they never actually told me this, but it would get back to me. some people just
don’t know how to deal with auggie, you
know? i nod. it’s not even like they know they’re being mean, she adds. they were
just scared. i mean, let’s face it, his face is a little scary, right? i guess, i
answer. but you’re okay with it? she asked me sweetly. you’re not too freaked out? or
scared? i’m not freaked out or scared. i smile. she nods and looks down at the
polar bear on her lap. i can’t tell whether she believes me or not, but then
she gives the polar bear a kiss on the nose and tosses it to me with a little
smile. i think that means she believes me.
or at least that she wants to Valentine's Day I GIVE OLIVIA a heart
necklace for valentine’s day, and she gives me a messenger bag she’s made out
of old floppy discs very cool how she makes things like that. earrings out of
pieces of circuit boards. dresses out of t-shirts. bags out of old jeans. she’s so
creative. i tell her she should be an artist someday, but she wants to be a
scientist. a geneticist, of all things. she wants to find cures for people like her
brother, i guess. we make plans for me to finally meet her parents. a mexican
restaurant on amford avenue near her house on saturday night. all day long i’m
nervous about it. and when i get nervous my ticks come out. i mean, my ticks are
always there, but they’re not like they used to be when i was little: nothing but
a few hard blinks now, the occasional head pull. but when i’m stressed out they
get worse— —and i’m definitely stressing about meeting her folks.
they’re waiting inside when i get to the restaurant. the dad gets up and shakes my
hand, and the mom gives me a hug. i give Augie a hello fist punch and kiss olivia
on the cheek before i sit down. it’s so
nice to meet you, justin! we’ve heard so much about you! her parents couldn’t be
nicer. put me at ease right away. the waiter brings over the menus and i
notice his expression the moment he lays eyes on august. but i pretend not to
notice. i guess we’re all pretending not to notice things tonight. the waiter. my
ticks the way august crushes the tortilla chips on the table and spoons
the crumbs into his mouth. i look at olivia and she smiles at me. she knows.
she sees the waiter’s face. she sees my ticks olivia is a girl who sees
everything. we spend the entire dinner talking and laughing. olivia’s parents
asked me about my music, how i got into the fiddle and stuff like that. and i
tell them about how i used to play classical violin but I got into
appalachin folk music and then zido and they’re listening to every word like
they’re really interested. they tell me to let them know the next time my band’s
playing a gig so they can come listen. i’m not used to all the attention,
to be truthful. my parents don’t have a clue about what I want to do with my
life. they never ask. we never talk like this. i don’t think they even know i
traded my Baro violin for an eight string hardanger fiddle two years ago.
after dinner we go back to olivia’s for some ice cream. their dog greets us at
the door. an old dog. super sweet she thrown up all over the hallway, though.
olivia’s mom rushes to get paper towels while the dad picks the dog up like
she’s a baby. what’s up old girly he says,
and the dog’s in heaven, tongue hanging out, tail wagging, legs in the air at
awkward angles. dad, tell justin how you got daisy, says olivia. yeah! says auggie.
the dad smiles and sits down in a chair with the dog still cradled in his arms.
it’s obvious he’s told this story lots
of times and they all love to hear it. so
i’m coming home from the subway one day, he says, and a homeless guy i’ve never
seen in this neighborhood before is pushing this floppy mut in a stroller,
and he comes up to me and says, hey, mister want to buy my dog? and without
even thinking about it, i say sure, how much you want? and he says 10 bucks, so i
give him the $20 i have in my wallet and
he hands me the dog. justin, i’m telling you, you’ve never smelled anything so bad
in your life! she stank so much i can’t
even tell you! so i took her right from there to the vet down the street and
then i brought her home. didn’t even call me first, by the way! the mom interjects
as she cleans the floor, to see if i’m okay with his bringing home some
homeless guy’s dog. the dog actually looks over at the mom when she says this,
like she understands everything everyone is saying about her. she’s a happy dog,
like she knows she looked out that day finding this family. i kind of know how
she feels. i like olivia’s family. they laugh a lot. my family is not like this
at all. my mom and dad got divorced when i was four and they pretty much hate
each other. i grew up spending half of every week in my dad’s apartment in
chelsea and the other half in my mom’s place in brooklyn heights. i have a half
brother who’s 5 years older than me and barely knows i exist. for as long as i
can remember I felt like my parents could hardly wait for me to be old
enough to take care of myself. “you can go to the store by yourself.” “here’s the key
to the apartment.” it’s funny how there’s a word like overprotective to describe
some parents, but no word that means the opposite.
what word do you use to describe parents who don’t protect enough
underprint volved lame? all of the above. olivia’s family tell each other “i
love you” all the time. i can’t remember the last time anyone in my family said
that to me. by the time i go home, my ticks have all
stopped our town WE’RE DOING THE play our town for the spring show this year.
olivia dares me to try out for the lead role, the stage manager, and somehow i get
it. total fluke. never got any lead roles in anything before. i tell olivia she
brings me good luck. unfortunately, she doesn’t get the female lead, emily gibbs.
the pinkhair girl named miranda gets it.
olivia gets a bit Park and is also the emily understudy. i’m actually more
disappointed than olivia is. she almost seems relieved. i don’t love people
staring at me, she says, which is sort of strange coming from such a pretty girl. a
part of me thinks maybe she blew her audition on purpose. the spring show is
at the end of april. it’s Middle March now, so that’s less than 6 weeks to
memorize my part. plus rehearsal time.
plus practicing with my band. plus finals.
plus spending time with olivia. it’s going to be a rough 6 weeks, that’s for
sure. mr. davenport, the drama teacher, is already manic about the
whole thing. will drive us crazy by the time it’s over, no doubt. i heard through
the grap Bine that he’d been planning on doing the elephant man but changed it to
our town at the last minute, and that change took a week off of our rehearsal
schedule. not looking forward to the craziness of the next month and a half
ladybug OLIVIA AND I are sitting on her front stoop. she’s helping me with my
lines. it’s a warm march evening, almost like summer. the sky is still bright cyan
but the sun is low and the sidewalks are stre with long shadows. i’m reciting: yes,
the sun’s come up over a thousand times.
summers and winters have cracked the mountains a little bit more and the
rains have brought down some of the dirt.
some babies that weren’t even born before have begun talking regular
sentences already; and a number of people who thought they were right young and
spry have noticed that they can’t bound up a flight of stairs like they used to,
without their heart fluttering a little.
i shake my head. can’t remember the rest.
all that can happen in a thousand days, olivia promises me, reading from the
script. right, right, right, i say, shaking my head. i sigh. i’m wiped, olivia. how the
heck am i going to remember all these lines?
you will, she answers confidently. she reaches out and cups her hands over a
ladybug that appears out of nowhere. see?
a good luck sign, she says, slowly lifting her top hand to reveal the ladybug
walking on the palm of her other hand.
good luck or just the hot weather, i joke.
of course good luck, she answers, watching the ladybug crawl up her wrist. there
should be a thing about making a wish on a
ladybug Augie and I used to do that with fireflies when we were little. she cups
her hands over the ladybug again. come on, make a wish. close your eyes. i dutifully
closed my eyes along second passes, then I opened them. did you make a wish? she
asked yep. she smiles, uncups her hands, and the ladybug, as if on Q spreads its
wings and flits away. don’t you want to know what I wished for? i asked kissing her.
no, she answered shyly, looking up at the sky, which, at this very moment, is the
exact color of her eyes. i made a wish, too, she says mysteriously that she has
so many things she could wish for I have no idea what she’s
thinking the bus stop OLIVIA’S MOM, AUGGIE jack, and daisy come down the
stoop just as i’m saying goodbye to olivia. slightly awkward since we are in
the middle of nice long kiss hi guys, says the mom, pretending not to see
anything, but the two boys are giggling.
hi, mrs. pullman. please call me Isabelle justin, she says again. it’s like the
third time she’s told me this, so i really need to start calling her that.
i’m heading home, i say, as if to explain.
oh, are you heading to the subway? she says, following the dog with a newspaper.
can you walk jack to the bus stop? no problem. that okay with you, jack? the mom
asked him, and he shrugs. justin, can you stay with him till the bus comes? of
course! we all say our goodbyes. olivia winks at
me. you don’t have to stay with me, says
jack as we’re walking up the block. i take the bus by myself all the time.
auggie’s mom is way too overprotective. he’s got a low grably
voice, like a little tough guy. he kind of looks like one of the those little
rascal kids in old black and white movies, like he should be wearing a news
boy cap and knickers. we get to the bus stop and the schedule says the bus will
be there in 8 minutes. i’ll wait with you,
i tell him. up to you. he shrugs. can i
borrow a dollar? i want some gum. i fish a dollar out of my pocket and watch him
cross the street to the grocery store on the corner. he seems too small to be
walking around by himself, somehow. then i think how i was that young when i was
taking the subway by myself. way too young. i’m going to be an overprotective
dad someday, i know it. my kids are going to know i care. i’m waiting there a
minute or two when i notice three kids walking up the block from the other
direction. they walk right past the grocery store, but one of them looks
inside and nudges the other two, and they all back up and look
inside. i can tell they’re up to no good, all elbowing each other other laughing.
one of them is jack’s height but the other two look much bigger, more like
teens. they hide behind the fruit stand in front of the store, and when jack
walks out, they trail behind him, making loud throwup noises. jack casually turns
around at the corner to see who they are and they run away, high-fiving each other
and laughing. little jerks. jack crosses the street like nothing happened and
stands next to me at the bus stop, blowing a bubble. friends of yours? i
finally say. ha, he says. he’s trying to
smile but i can see he’s upset. just some
jerks from my school, he says. a kid named julian and his two gorillas, henry and
miles. do they bother you like that a lot?
no, they’ve never done that before they never do that in school or they get
kicked out. julian lives two blocks from here, so I guess it was just bad luck
running into him. oh, okay. i know nod. it’s
not a big deal, he assures me. we both automatically look down asford avenue to
see if the bus is coming. we’re sort of in a war, he says
after a minute, as if that explains everything. then he pulls out this
crumpled piece of loose leaf paper from his jean pocket and gives it to me. i
unfold it, and it’s a list of names in three columns. he’s turned the whole
grade against me, says jack. not the whole grade great i point out, looking down at
the list. he leaves me notes in my locker that say stuff like everybody hates you
you should tell your teacher about that.
jack looks at me like i’m an idiot and shakes his head. anyway, you have all
these neutrals, i said pointing to the list. if you get them on your side, things
will even up a bit. yeah, well, that’s really going to happen, he says
sarcastically. why not? he shoots me another look like like i am absolutely
the stupidest guy he’s ever talked to in the world. what? i say. he shakes his head
like i’m hopeless. let’s just say, he says, i’m friends with someone who isn’t
exactly the most popular kid in the school. then it hits me what he’s not
coming out insane august. this is all about his being friends with august. and
he doesn’t want to tell me because i’m the sister’s boyfriend. yeah,
of course, makes sense. we see the bus coming down asford avenue. well, just hang
in there, i tell him, handing back the paper. middle school is about as bad as
it gets, and then it gets better everything will work out. he shrugs and
shoves the list back into his pocket. we wave by when he gets on the bus, and i
watch it pull away. when i get to the subway station two blocks away, i see the
same three kids hanging out in front of the bagel place next door.
they’re still laughing and yuck yucking each other like they’re some kind of
gang bangers little rich boys in expensive skinny jeans acting tough.
don’t know what possesses me, but i take my glasses off, put them in my pocket, and
tuck my fiddle case under my arm so the pointy side is facing up. i walk over to
them, my face scrunched up mean looking they look at me, laughs dying on their
lips when they see me, ice cream cones at odd angles.
yo, listen up. don’t mess with jack, i say really slowly, gritting my teeth, my voice
all clint eastwood tough guy mess with him again and you will be very, very
sorry. and then i tap my fiddle case for effect. got it? they nod in unison, ice
cream dripping onto their hands. good. i nod mysteriously, then sprint down the
subway two steps at a time rehearsal THE PLAY IS taking up most of
my time as we get closer to opening night. lots of lines to remember. long
monologues where it’s just me talking.
olivia had this great idea, though, and it’s helping. i have my fiddle with me on
stage and play it a bit while i’m talking. It’s not written that way, but mr.
davenport thinks it adds an extra folksy element to have the stage manager
plucking on a fiddle. and for me it’s so great because whenever i need a second
to remember my next line, i just start playing a little “soldier’s joy” on my
fiddle and it buys me some time. i’ve gotten to know the kids in the show a
lot better, especially the pink-haired girl who plays emily. turns out she’s not
nearly as stuck up as i thought she was, given the crowd she hangs out with. her
boyfriend’s this built jock who’s a big deal on the varsity sports circuit at
school. it’s a whole world that i have nothing nothing to do with, so i’m kind
of surprised that this miranda girl turns out to be kind of nice. one day
we’re sitting on the floor backstage waiting for the tech guys to fix the main
spotlight. so how long have you and olivia been dating? she asks out of the
blue. about 4 months now, i say. have you met her brother? she says casually. it’s
so unexpected that i can’t hide my surprise. you know olivia’s brother? i
asked via didn’t tell you? we used to be good friends. i’ve known auggie since he
was a baby. oh, yeah, i think i knew that, i
answer. i don’t want to let on that olivia had not told me any of this. i
don’t want to let on how surprised i am that she called her via. nobody but
olivia’s family calls her via, and here this pinkhair girl, who i thought was a
stranger, is calling her via. miranda laughs and shakes her her head but she
doesn’t say anything. there’s an awkward silence and then she starts fishing
through her bag and pulls out her wallet.
she rifles through a couple of pictures and then hands one to me. it’s of a
little boy in a park on a sunny day. he’s wearing shorts and a t-shirt— —and an
astronaut helmet that covers his entire head. it was like 100° that day, she says,
smiling at the picture. but he wouldn’t take that helmet off for anything. he for
like 2 years straight, in the winter, in the summer, at the beach. it was crazy.
yeah, i’ve seen pictures in olivia’s house. i’m the one who gave him that
helmet, she says. she sounds a little proud of that. she takes the picture and
carefully inserts it back into her wallet. cool, i answer. so you’re okay with
it? she says, looking at me. i look at her blankly. okay with what? she raises her
eyebrows like she doesn’t believe me. you know what i’m talking about, she says, and
takes a long drink from her water bottle.
let’s face it, she continues, the universe was not kind to auggie pulman
bird WHY DIDN’T YOU tell me that you and miranda nevas used to be friends? i say
to olivia the next day. i’m really annoyed at her for not telling me this.
it’s not a big deal, she answers defensively, looking at me like i’m weird.
it is a big deal, i say. i look like an
idiot. how could you not tell me? you’ve always acted like you don’t even know
her. i don’t know her, she answers quickly.
i don’t know who that pink-haired cheerleader is. the girl i know was a
total dork who collected american girl dolls. oh come on, olivia. you come on! you
could have mentioned it to me at some point, i say quietly, pretending not to
notice the big fat tear that’s suddenly rolling down her cheek. she shrugs, fighting back bigger
tears. it’s okay, i’m not mad, i say, thinking the tears are about me. i
honestly don’t care if you’re mad, she says spitefully. oh, that’s real nice, i fire
back. she doesn’t say anything. the tears are about to come. olivia, what’s the
matter? i say. she shakes her head like she doesn’t want to talk about it, but
all of a sudden the tears start rolling
a mile a minute. i’m sorry, it’s not you,
justin. i’m not crying because of you, she finally says through her tears. then why
are you crying? because i’m an awful person. what are you talking about? she’s
not looking at me, wiping her tears with the palm of her hand. i haven’t told my
parents about the show, she says quickly.
i shake my head because i don’t quite
get what she’s telling me. that’s okay, i say. it’s not too late,
there are still tickets available— i don’t want them to come to the show,
justin, she interrupts impatiently. don’t you see what i’m saying? i don’t want
them to come! if they come, they’ll bring auggie with them, and i just don’t feel
like here she’s hit by another round of crying that doesn’t let her finish
talking. i put my arm around her. i’m an awful person! she says through her tears.
you’re not an awful person, i say softly.
yes i am! she sobbs it’s just been so nice being in a new school where nobody
knows about him, you know? nobody’s whispering about it behind my back. it’s
just been so nice, justin. but if he comes to the play, then everyone will talk
about it, everyone will know. i don’t know
why i’m feeling like this. i swear i’ve never been embarrassed by him before. i
know, i know, i say, soothing her. you’re entitled, olivia. you’ve dealt with a lot
your whole life. olivia reminds me of a bird sometimes, how her feathers get all
ruffled when she’s mad. and when she’s fragile like this, she’s a little lost
bird looking for its nest. so i give her my wing to hide under the
Universe I CAN’T SLEEP tonight. my head is full of thoughts that won’t turn off.
lines from my monologues. elements of the periodic table that i’m supposed to be memorizing
theams i’m supposed to be understanding.
olivia. auggie. miranda’s words keep coming back: the universe was not kind to
auggie pman i’m thinking about that a lot and everything it means. she’s right
about that. the universe was not kind to auggie pullman. what did that little kid
ever do to deserve his sentence? what did the parents do? or olivia? she once
mentioned that some doctor told her parents that the odds of someone getting
the same combination of syndromes that came together to make auggie’s face are
like one in four million. so doesn’t that make the universe a giant lottery, then?
you purchase a ticket when you’re born.
and it’s all just random whether you get
a good ticket or a bad ticket. it’s all just
luck. my head swirls on this, but then softer thoughts soothe, like a flatted
third on a major cord no, no, it’s not all
random, if it really was all random, the universe would abandon us completely. and
the universe doesn’t. it takes care of its most fragile creations and ways we
can’t see. like with parents who adore you blindly. and a big sister who feels
guilty for being human over you. and a little grably voiced kid whose friends
have left him over you. and even a pink-haired girl who carries your
picture in her wallet. maybe it is a lottery, but the universe makes it all
even out in the end. the universe takes care of all its birds thanks for listening please
remember to like and subscribe and if you want become a channel member we'll see you next time